Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company records LSC.1434
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Corporate History, 1911, 1922-2007
  - Ivan J. Houston files, 1970-2000
    Ivan J. Houston, son of Norman O. Houston, was born in Los Angeles, California in 1925, the same year his father co-founded Golden State Guarantee Fund Insurance Company. In 1943 he enlisted in the Army and in 1944 he was assigned to the 3rd Battalion, 370th Infantry Regiment Combat Team, 92nd Infantry Division of the U.S. Fifth Army, also known as the Buffalo Soldiers. Houston returned from service to continue his education at the University of California at Berkeley. He worked at Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company for more than forty years, including at the executive level when he became President and CEO in 1970 and Chairman in 1980, a position he held until his retirement in 1990.
    - Speeches Vol. I - A (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Speeches Vol. I - B (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Speeches Vol. I - C (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Speeches Vol. I - D (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Speeches Vol. I - F (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Speeches Vol. I - G (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - Speeches Vol. I - H (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Speeches Vol. I - I (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Speeches Vol. I - L (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - Speeches Vol. I - M (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - Speeches Vol. I - N (Box 25, Folder 11)
    - Speeches Vol. I - O (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Speeches Vol. I - PQ (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Speeches Vol. I - S (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Speeches Vol. I - T (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Speeches Vol. I - W (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Speeches Vol. II - A (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Speeches Vol. II - B (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Speeches Vol. II - B (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - Speeches Vol. II - G (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - Speeches Vol. II - IJ (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - Speeches Vol. II - M (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Speeches Vol. II - N (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Speeches Vol. II - O (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Speeches Vol. II - PQ (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Speeches Vol. II - R (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Speeches Vol. II - S (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Speeches Vol. II - V (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Corporate History (Box 27, Folder 8)
      Materials include correspondence between Ivan J. Houston and Almena Lomax concerning her drafts of the company's history.
    - GSM Historical Archives (Box 27, Folder 9)
      Materials include Houston's correspondence with UCLA Library Special Collections concerning his donation of the Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company records, the deed of gift for collection 1434, an inventory for the first accession of this collection, and his UCLA Oral History Agreement.
    - Time Capsule, 2000 July 21 (Box 27, Folder 10-11)
      Materials include the Time Capsule Program and a list of "cornerstone" documents that were placed in the time capsule which is to be opened on GSM's 125th Anniversary.
  - Verna A. Hickman files, 1925-1975, 1981
    Born in Oakhurst, Texas on March 2, 1908, Verna Alvis Stratten Hickman was the child of GSM Founder William Nickerson Jr.'s sister Rosetta. Rosetta Nickerson became a school teacher, married and moved to Los Angeles at about the same time as her brother, and early enough for Verna to attend Los Angeles Public Schools and attend the University of Southern California as a special student in Journalism and Business Administration. At the age of 18, Hickman went to work for Golden State Mutual in 1926, its second year in operation. She began as George A. Beavers, Jr.'s secretary and her organizational climb reads as follows: 1927, Administrative Secretary; 1944, Supervisor Public Relations; 1949, Public Relations Administrator, Junior Officer; 1954, Agency Secretary; 1960, Agency Administrative Officer; 1964, Policyowner Service Officer; 1967, Vice-President - Assistant Treasurer; and 1969, Vice-President - Secretary and Treasurer. Hickman was a member of the Public Relations Society of America, the Life Advertisers Association, the National Association of Colored Women's Clubs and served as President of the Wilfandel Club. She earned the Urban League Achievement Award in 1951 for her work as a pioneer in the field of Public Relations. Hickman helped develop Golden State Mutual's award-winning Public Relations Department and became GSM's second woman senior officer.
    - Organization/Company File I (Box 28, Folder 1)
      Materials include reports, procedures, organizational charts, company releases, memos that document organization changes, correspondence and job descriptions.
    - Organization/Company File II, 1948-1973 (Box 28, Folder 2)
      Materials include by-laws, resolutions, correspondence, memos that document organization changes, copies of GSM Messengers (1948-1949) and a copy of "In the GSM Spotlight" which includes employee rankings.
    - Public Relations, 1941-1957 (Box 28, Folder 3)
      Materials include results of an investigation of theory and practices of public relations function, public relations committee minutes, historical review of advertising-sales promotion-public relations functions at GSM, correspondence and reports.
    - List of charter policyowners and clippings, 1925-1945 (Box 29, Folder 1)
      Materials also include Hickman's GSM history, "Fate Tipped the Scales," Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company (Full Legal Reserves Maintained) publication and additional corporate history drafts.
    - The United Golden State Court of Inhuman Relations, circa 1930s (Box 29, Folder 2)
      Script with an attached memo from Edgar Johnson that reads, "This skit was performed as a rally occasion back in the 30's. It is historical and should be preserved."
    - Conventions (incomplete), 1939 (Box 29, Folder 3)
      Copies of prize-winning student essays for a nationwide essay contest sponsored by the National Negro Insurance Association on the subject of "The Relation of Insurance Service to the Economic Needs of the Negro."
    - Library scrapbooks, 1937-1952 (Box 29, Folder 4)
      Materials include songbooks, premium notice reminders pamphlets, cookbooks, certificates of advancement pamphlets and birthday greeting cards.
    - Personality of the Week and Woman of the Month profiles, 1942-1954 (Box 29, Folder 5)
      Profiles of GSM employees with accompanying photos. Hickman wrote the Woman of the Month profiles which were published in the GSM Messenger.
    - History file - V.A.H., 1947-1952 (Box 29, Folder 6)
      Materials include Hickman's press release for the GSM Murals on California History, Department Heads Meeting minutes, 1999 West Adams Boulevard construction reports, reorganization announcements, correspondence from citizens requesting GSM history and Hickman's responses, a script for church greetings and invitation to tour home office building and "Brief History of Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company."
    - Copyright applications, 1948 (Box 29, Folder 7)
      Two certificates of registration for the following books: Golden State Mutual Insurance Success Measurement System and Golden State Mutual Training Plan.
    - Messenger news memos, 1949-1953 (Box 29, Folder 8)
      Memos concerning policies, format and content of the GSM publication, The Messenger.
    - Home Office Open House memos and announcements (Box 29, Folder 9-11)
      Materials also include booklets, mailers, information sheets and correspondence concerning the opening of GSM's new home office on Adams Boulevard at Western Avenue.
    - Rules and Regulations Governing Agents, 1963-1969 (Box 29, Folder 12)
      Materials include Hickman's copies of rules and regulations booklets as well as non-union employee booklets and booklets on grievance report and inquiry procedure for employees.
    - Correspondence and tour guide manual, 1949 (Box 30, Folder 1)
      Materials include Hickman's thank you letters to community members for the successful home office opening and unveiling of historic Negro murals as well as an open house tour guide manual.
    - Public Relations materials, 1949-1972 (Box 30, Folder 2)
      Materials include New Home Office Opening booklet, The GSM Story publication, a list of GSM Board Members, Your New Home Office invitations, company information sheets, Facts About Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company, The Founding of Golden State Mutual document, George A. Beavers, Jr.'s timeline of the company's foundation, George A. Beavers, Jr.'s Building Dedication Speech transcript and Personal History Recollections and GSM's History in Northern California transcript.
    - National Negro Insurance Association Convention file, 1950 (Box 30, Folder 3)
      Materials include GSM expense schedules and committee meeting minutes.
    - GSM History, 1950-1954 (Box 30, Folder 4-5)
      Materials include correspondence concerning the Lincoln Lecture by Dr. Louis A. Warren of Lincoln National Life Insurance, Home Office Topics publications, Management News, departmental salary cards, "Every Tub" song contest submissions, Six for Twenty-Six Campaign correspondence and an envelope containing models for company rings and a sound recording disc.
    - 27th Anniversary Campaign, 1952 (Box 30, Folder 6)
      Correspondence concerning GSM's Silver Anniversary, 26th and 27th anniversaries.
    - The Golden Rule and GSM Trademark correspondence and photos, 1953-1959 (Box 30, Folder 7)
      Materials include photos of the Golden Rule Marble in Betty Wallace's hand, copy of the article, "What Shall Man Live By?," memos discussing the Golden Rule as a GSM cornerstone and correspondence, press release drafts and sketches concerning GSM's sunburst trademark.
    - Articles of Incorporation, 1975 (Box 30, Folder 8)
      Materials include official Articles of Incorporation signed by President Ernest Shell and Secretary Verna A. Hickman and associated Voting Membership Certificates with signatures of receipt from members.
    - Management News, 1954 November 15 (Box 31, Folder 1)
      Includes an attached memo that discusses its discontinued status, its importance and the possibility of its revival.
    - Supplement to Instructions for Writing New Sickness and Accident Policies, 1954 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Premium Schedule Policy Form 108-53 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - Nickerson Gardens, 1954 (Box 31, Folder 4)
      Materials include Hot Topics release on the William Nickerson, Jr. Gardens opening, Star Review clipping concerning the Nickerson Gardens Baby Clinic opening and Journal of Housing feature which includes interior and exterior photos and floor plans.
    - GSM History Diary, 1954 (Box 31, Folder 5)
      This diary is typed and handwritten. Hickman mentions on the cover that the running notes for this diary began in 1954 and, therefore, this is not a complete record.
    - Management News, 1954-1955 (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - 5th Lithographic Awards Competition Catalog (Box 31, Folder 7)
      GSM letterhead and envelopes received first place prize and are featured on page 32.
    - Press Releases, 1955 (Box 31, Folder 8)
      All releases are authored by Hickman in her role as Agency Secretary.
    - 30th Anniversary Campaign proposal, 1955 (Box 31, Folder 9)
      Materials also include correspondence and lists of charter policyowners.
    - Company clippings, publications and press releases, 1955-1956 (Box 31, Folder 10)
      Materials include Man With the Golden Pen promotional brochures, mailing folders, memo pads and Jet magazines.
    - Our Authors Study Club correspondence, 1955, 1957, 1958 (Box 31, Folder 11)
      Three letters from Vassie D. Wright, Founder and President of Our Authors Study Club, the Los Angeles Branch of the Association for the Study of Negro Life and History discuss membership dues, the Journal of Negro History and the Club's annual Negro History Week observance. Under Wright's leadership, the first city-wide Negro History Week celebrations were initiated in February, 1949, an observance which grew to become Black History Month.
    - Historical Review, 1957 April 1 (Box 31, Folder 12)
      Materials include a copy of the five page "Historical Review of Development and Conduct of Advertising-Sales Promotional-Public Relations Functions at GSM."
    - The ABC Picture Book of Eminent Negroes Past and Present, 1959-1962 (Box 31, Folder 13)
      Materials also include correspondence and discussion of the book's inclusion of GSM Founder William Nickerson, Jr., President Norman O. Houston and Chairman of the Board George A. Beavers, Jr.
    - Pictorial Review, 1960 (Box 31, Folder 14)
      Materials include multiple copies of this special edition of The Messenger celebrating 35 years of Golden State Mutual history.
    - Bradley Now and A Matter of Color posters, 1969 (Box 31, Folder 15)
      Materials include one Bradley for Mayor campaign poster and two A Matter of Color posters published by Studio Watts.
    - Obsequies, 1972, 1973, 1981 (Box 31, Folder 16)
      Materials include funeral programs for Luther Martin Hudson, Bertha Benton Nickerson and Norman O. Houston.
    - A Great Day in December program, 1974 (Box 31, Folder 17)
      Materials include Tom Bradley Inaugural program and dinner invitation.
    - Bio files - V.A.H., 1944-1972 (Box 31, Folder 18-24, Box 32, Folder 1-15)
      Verna A. Hickman's biography files are organized alphabetically, include biographical notes and press releases composed by Hickman and may also contain resumes, GSM biographical questionnaires and clippings. The majority of the files are for GSM employees but there are also files for Board members and community leaders.
      Box 31: Includes bio files for the following: Helen E. Batiste, George A. Beavers, Jr., Byron Beverly, Ike Blocker, Roscoe C. Carroll, Johnnie L. Cochran, Sr. and Verna A. Hickman.
      Box 32: Includes bio files for the following employees: Ivan J. Houston, Norman B. Houston, Norman O. Houston, Luther M. Hudson, Edgar J. Johnson, Simon P. Johnson, Lonzie Lee Jones, Raphael O'Hara Lanier, Charles H. Matthews, William Nickerson, Jr., William E. Pajaud, Mercer Zimmerman Ray, Robert Webster Smith, Dr. Henry Howard Towles and A.J. Kelly Williams.
    - Bio files - Company (Box 32, Folder 16-21, Box 33, Box 34, Box 35, Box 36, Box 37, Box 38, Folder 1-15)
      Files are organized alphabetically and include biographical data sheets and photos of employees from the Home Office and District Offices. There are also files for some Board Members, community leaders and artists such as GSM mural artist Charles Alston.
      Box 32: Charles Alston - Gloria Beasley. This box includes Helen E. Batiste's file, GSM's first employee.
      Box 33: George A. Beavers, Jr. - Fern L. Ford. The Beavers file also includes the following handwritten and typed speeches: "Dodger Stadium Dedication," "Nickerson Month Rally," "GSM 50th Anniversary Celebration," "The Space Age Challenge," "Football Rally Speech in Oakland," "The Three R's of Citizenship," "A Salute to GSM's 1968 Champions," "Building With Service" and "Gearing the Agency to Meet Company Needs."
      Box 34: Field representatives - Ivan J. Houston. This box includes files for Leonard M. Grimes, Verna A. Hickman and Ivan A. Houston, as well as a file of Home Office employee biographical data sheets.
      Box 35: Norman O. Houston - Edgar J. Johnson. This box includes files for Norman B. Houston and Stephen A. Johns. The Edgar J. Johnson files include his typed and annotated speeches such as "What was it like in 1925?" which he wrote in 1963 when he was GSM Executive Vice President.
      Box 36: Lonzie L. Jones - Board Member Hector Orci. This box includes files for Thomas Kilgore, Board Member Charles H. Matthews, Detroit Urban League Executive Director Frances E. Kornegay, Thaddieus B. McCray, Bertha B. Nickerson and Founder William Nickerson, Jr.
      Box 37: Kwasi Osei - J.D. Tanner. This box includes files for Golden State Minority Foundation President Ernest Shell and artist William E. Pajaud who served as GSM Vice President, Secretary, Director of Public Relations and Advertising and Art Collection Curator.
      Box 38: Larkin Teasley - Rory Wayne Wright. This box includes files for Harold E. Toliver, Medical Director and Board Member Dr. H.H. Towles, A.J. "Kelly" Williams and Home Office Architect Paul R. Williams. Teasley's files include Agent Victor A. Nickerson's 1935 GSM Manual.
  - Titus Alexander files, 1911, 1922-1969, undated
    Titus Alexander was an engineer who came to Los Angeles in 1897 and a self-described "volunteer curator of Negro history." Alexander was also a California Historical Society Board Member who assisted Los Angeles Librarian Miriam Matthews with her research for the GSM murals that document the Negro in California history. On June 4, 1952, GSM President Norman O. Houston announced the establishment in its Library of the Titus Alexander Collection of Negro Life and History and presented Alexander with a bookplate to be placed in the volumes. The original volumes in this collection were donated by Alexander in 1950 and the bookplate was created in honor and appreciation for his generous gift of books and his interest in the cultural life of his community.
    The research files that follow the Biddy Mason files are organized chronologically and then shift to alphabetical arrangement. Alexander's research files on the contributions of Black people to American and particularly California history were integrated into the GSM Library's vertical files and inspired other vertical files. Items in the collection often include Alexander's signature and annotations.
    - Clippings, biography and bookplate (Box 38, Folder 16)
      Materials also include a copy of Alexander's California Historical Society membership card, a Gray Flexograph recording of Alexander's funeral oration for his friend Mr. William Atwood and photographs of the Titus Alexander bookplate presentation which feature Vermont Square Branch Librarian Miriam Matthews, President Norman O. Houston, GSM Librarian Mamie Spencer, Southern California Historical Society Executive Committee Chairman Gregg Layne, Public Relations Administrator Verna A. Hickman and George A. Beavers, Jr., Board Chairman and Treasurer.
    - Alexander Collection inventory (Box 38, Folder 17)
      Inventory of the Titus Alexander Collection of Negro Life and History books, photos and research files.
    - Collection of Negro Life and History: Books (Box 38, Box 39, Box 40)
      Box 38: Titles include Bernheimer Oriental Gardens, Dr. George Washington Carver Scientist, An Economic Detour, Lincoln's Gettysburg Address and First and Second Inaugural Addresses and Your Most Humble Servant.
      Box 39: Titles include History of the Great Rebellion, How He Ran Across the Continent to Help an Invalid Father, The Negro Handbook, Negro Servitude in Illinois, Negro Servitude in Illinois, Negro Yearbook 1931-1932 and Negro Yearbook 1947. Materials also include First Aid For Books Handibook Vol. I.
      Box 40: Titles include The Negro in American Business, A New Negro for A New Century, The Story of My Life and Work, The Uprising of A Great People, Races and Immigrants in America, Studies in Historical Method, Negro Who's Who in California, The Progress of the Negro Race and Who's Who in Colored America.
    - Biddy Mason files (Box 41)
      Biddy Mason arrived in California as a slave late in 1851. She won freedom for herself and her three daughters in a Los Angeles court room on January 19, 1856. Once free, she worked as a midwife and nurse for Dr. John Griffin, a Los Angeles physician. When she had saved enough money in 1865, she bought four large lots in the block between Spring and Broadway and Fourth and Third Streets. It was in Biddy Mason's home on Spring Street between 3rd and 4th where the first Black church in Los Angeles, now the First African Methodist Episcopal (A.M.E.) Church, was organized in 1872. On January 6, 1971, the Cultural Heritage Board of the City of Los Angeles named the First A.M.E. Church building at 801 Towne Avenue Los Angeles Historic-Cultural Monument No. 71.
      Materials include photos of Mason, her family and the Owens house, newspaper clippings, original manuscripts entitled "My Grandfather" and "Autobiography" by Mason's grandson Robert C. Owens, copies of Mason's land deeds and freedom papers, Pioneers of Negro Origin in California book, Biddy Mason Cultural Center pamphlets, Federation of Black History and Arts, Inc. Advisory Board Meeting minutes, Biddy Mason excerpt from "The Negro Trail Blazers of California," Program for "Biddy Mason Day," original request to borrow Biddy Mason materials from GSM signed by Miriam Matthews, "Dime for Biddy Mason Day" promotional flyers and correspondence from Chairman Jerome Scott to GSM's Director of Sales William E. Pajaud, draft of mission and vision for The Biddy Mason Center, press release concerning the First A.M.E. Church building's Historic-Cultural Monument designation, The Book of Common Prayer and The Hymnal book.
    - Negro Insurance Company Reports, 1937-1955 (Box 42, Folder 1)
    - National Negro Insurance Association publications, 1938-1956 (Box 42, Folder 2-3)
    - Employment publications, clippings and surveys, 1939-1954 (Box 42, Folder 4)
      Materials include the following publications: The Negro in the Brewing Industry, Negroes in the Work Group and The Urban Negro Worker in the United States.
    - American Negroes publications, 1940, 1944, 1948 (Box 42, Folder 5)
      Materials include The Negro in America, Cavalcade of the American Negro and Race Relations in the United States: 1917-1947 by W.E.B. Du Bois.
    - Armed Services publications, 1942-1950 (Box 42, Folder 6)
      Materials include "Nobody knows...," Freedom to Serve, Win the War - Win the Peace, U.S. Army Divisions in the World War and Negroes and the War.
    - Housing publications and clippings, 1947-1954 (Box 42, Folder 7)
      Materials include Covenants for Exclusion, What you should know about Neighborhood Redevelopment Corporations, If Your Next Neighbors Are Negroes, Mortgage Financing for Properties Available to Negroes, The Road Back, Hemmed In, Housing of the Nonwhite Population, Homes for Aryans Only and The Housing of Negro Veterans.
    - Negro biography clippings and publication (Box 43, Folder 1)
    - Africa publications and clippings, 1947, 1955 (Box 43, Folder 2)
      Materials include The Real Facts About Ethiopia and Your Questions Answered by the Accra Town Council.
    - Foreign Affairs: An American Quarterly Review, 1948 October (Box 43, Folder 3)
    - Science publications and clippings, 1949-1951 (Box 43, Folder 4)
    - Education publications and clippings, 1949-1955 (Box 43, Folder 5)
      Materials include the following pamphlets: Prejudice in Textbooks, Readings in Intergroup Relations, Religion and Race: Barriers to College? and Discrimination in Higher Education.
    - Fair Employment Practices Legislation publications, circa 1950 (Box 43, Folder 6)
      Materials include The Dynamics of State Campaigns for Fair Employment Practices Legislation, Your Rights Under State and Local Fair Employment Practices Laws and Speaking About the Right of Every Person to Earn a Living.... For an Ordinance to Abolish Job Discrimination in Los Angeles.
    - Socialism for Millionaires, undated (Box 43, Folder 7)
      This miniature book was written by George Bernard Shaw and published by Little Leather Library Corporation, New York.
    - Americanism clippings and publications, 1922-1953 (Box 43, Folder 8)
      Materials include Are You an American? Great Americans Speak, The City of Los Angeles: The First 100 Years and 100 Amazing Facts About the Negro with Complete Proof.
    - Black history clippings, 1949-1969 (Box 44, Folder 1-2)
    - Black organizations clippings, 1949-1956 (Box 44, Folder 3)
    - The Dawn of a New Day for the Negro, 1949 (Box 44, Folder 4)